Register of the Aleta Brownlee Papers, 1945-1950.
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleta Brownlee Papers,
1945-1950.
69059
Brownlee, Aleta.
9 manuscript boxes (3.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs and office files, relating to UNRRA and IRO relief work for displaced children in Austria at the end of World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1969.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
International Refugee Organization.; United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.; Child welfare--Austria.; International relief.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Austria.; World War, 1939-1945--Children.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; Austria.
Biographical History.
Aleta Brownlee began her employment with the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration as a Welfare Specialist on the Yugoslavian Mission in 1945. Later that year she was transferred to Vienna and promoted to Director of Child Welfare in Austria. In that position, both with UNRRA and with the International Refugee Organization (which superceded UNRRA in 1947), she worked with displaced children. The Child Welfare Agency had the responsibility of locating and reestablishing, either through repatriation or resettlement, children who had been moved from their homelands during the war. Ms. Brownlee continued this work until 1950 when the International Refugee Organization ceased its activities.
The collection consists almost exclusively of UNRAA and IRO documents. Of these, a small number relate to the Welfare Program in Yugoslavia directly after the war. The overwhelming majority of documents, however, concerns the location and reestablishment of orphans and children separated from their parents. Approximately 35% of the collection is comprised of case files, complete with the children's histories and their eventual placement. Occasionally there is follow-up correspondence from the children. The remainder of the UNRRA and IRO documents concern the problems of finding children absorbed by the Third Reich and what should be done with them once found. The correspondence, memoranda and transcripts of meetings relating to the specific problems of Polish, Yugoslavian and Russian refugees are the most complete. Included in the collection is documentation relating to the roles played by various national chapters of the Red Cross and by the French, American, British and Soviet military governments. Considered all together, the UNRRA and IRO documents chronicle both the operations and the results of the Child Welfare Program in Austria from 1945 to 1950.
Also included in the collection is a manuscript, "Whose Children?," written by Aleta Brownlee ca. 1950-1951 concerning her experiences with UNRRA and IRO. In addition there is a very small miscellany file.
Series Description
- Office File, 1945-1950. (Box No. 1-9.)
  Memoranda, reports, correspondence, interview transcripts, etc. pertaining to the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration's welfare mission in Yugoslavia and the International Refugee Organization, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Writings, 1950-1951. (Box No. 9.)
  One manuscript, "Whose Children?"
- Miscellany, 1950-1952. (Box No. 9.)
  Printed items, arranged chronologically.
Container List
- OFFICE FILE, 1945-1950
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration -Welfare (Box 1-9.)
    - Displaced Persons Program
      - Letters, reports, memoranda and interviews, 1945-1946, compiled by A. Brownlee. Includes calendar of documents (3)
    - Yugoslavian Mission, 1945
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration/International Refugee Organization
    - Displaced Persons
      - Children
        - Argentinian, 1946
        - Austrian, 1946-1949
        - Belgian, 1946-1949
        - Case loads, analyses of monthly reports
          - June 1949-December 1949
          - January 1950-June 1950
        - Cases
          - Fragmentary
          - "A"
          - "B" (5) (Box 2.)
          - "C"
          - "D" (2)
          - "E" (Box 3.)
          - "F" (2)
          - "G" (2)
          - "H" (2)
          - "J"
          - "K"
          - "L"
          - "M" (2) (Box 4.)
          - "N"
          - "P" (2)
          - "R"
          - "S" (3)
          - "T"
          - "U"
          - "V"
          - "W" (Box 5.)
          - "Z"
        - "Child Welfare in the Displaced Persons Programme." Report, 1947
        - Children receiving assistance, 1947-1950
        - Correspondence, 1946-1950
        - Czechoslovakian, 1946-1949
        - Danish, 1946
        - Dutch, 1946-1948
        - Ethnic German (Volksdeutsche), 1945-1949
        - German, 1946-1948
        - Greek, 1947-1948
        - Hungarian, 1946-1950
        - Italian, 1947-1948
        - Jewish, 1946-1949
        - Legal status, 1947-1949
        - "List of Children Repatriated, Resettled, or Otherwise Reestablished by UNRRA or IRO, 1946-1950." Report, 1951
        - Non-Austrians living in Austria, 1946-1950
        - Policy
          - General, 1946-1949
          - Adoption (Box 6.)
            - Undated, 1945
            - 1946
            - 1947
            - 1948
            - 1949
            - 1950
          - Eligibility, 1946-1950
          - Procedures, 1946-1948
          - Repatriation, 1946-1950
          - Resettlement, 1947-1949
          - Standards of care, 1946-1949
        - Polish
          - Undated
          - 1945
          - 1946
          - 1947
          - 1948
          - 1949
            - "Master List of Polish Children Processed by Lebensborn and Heimschule in terms of Directive 67/I compiled by the Documents and Intelligence Section of I.T.S., Child Search Branch," April 1949
          - 1950
        - Polish Ukrainians, 1946-1947
        - Resettlement
          - General, 1946-1950
          - Australia, 1949-1950
          - Canada, 1947-1950
          - Chile, 1948
          - France, 1948 (Box 7.)
          - Great Britain, 1947-1949
          - Handicapped, 1948-1950
          - New Zealand, 1949
          - Paraguay, 1946-1948
          - Sweden, 1948-1950
          - Transportation, 1948-1949
          - United States
            - Undated
            - 1946
            - 1947
            - 1948
            - 1949
            - 1950
        - Rumanian, 1946-1949
        - Russian
          - Undated
          - 1946
          - 1947
          - 1948
          - 1949
          - 1950
        - Tracing
          - Undated
          - 1946
          - 1947
          - 1948
          - 1949 (Box 8.)
          - "Lebensborn Report - An Outline of the Structure and Practices of Lebensborn for Guidance in Child Search," 1948
          - "Nazional-Sozialistische Volkswohlfahrt" (National Socialist Welfare Agency) Copies and translations of official NSDAP documents relating to the appropriation of foreign children as German citizes, 1938-1944
          - "S.S. Lebensborn Activities in Upper Austria," by Wilhelmina Van Dop, ca. 1947
        - Turkish, 1947
        - "UNRRA Closure Report on United Nations Unaccompanied Children in Germany," June, 1947
        - Yugoslavian
          - Undated
          - 1945
          - 1946
          - 1947
          - 1948
          - 1949
          - 1950
        - Miscellaneous, 1946-1950
      - Citizenship, Austrian, 1945-1950
      - Policy - General, 1946-1950
      - "Psychological Problems of Displaced Persons." Report, 1945
    - Operations
      - American Zone
        - Children's Home
          - Undated
          - 1946
          - 1947 (Box 9.)
          - 1949
          - 1950
        - Youth Center, 1948-1950
      - British Zone
        - General, 1946-1948
        - Children's Home
          - Undated
          - 1945
          - 1946
          - 1947
          - 1948
          - 1949
          - 1950
      - French Zone - General, 1946-1948
      - Vienna - General, 1946, 1950
    - Personnel, 1945-1948
- WRITINGS, 1950-1951
  - "Whose Children?" Typescript, ca. 1950-1951 (3) (Box 9.)
- MISCELLANY, 1950-1952
  - Comic book, Czechoslovakian, ca. 1950 and printed articles (Box 9.)